<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-05-13T17:05:12-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Steven Daniels</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Manager as a Multiplier</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/05/01/manager-as-a-multiplier.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Manager as a Multiplier" /><published>2018-05-01T16:07:23-04:00</published><updated>2018-05-01T16:07:23-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/05/01/manager-as-a-multiplier</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/05/01/manager-as-a-multiplier.html">&lt;p&gt;It’s not always easy to pin down what managers do, but one thing is for sure: bad managers hurt teams. It’s an accepted truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve spent a good amount of time thinking about why bad managers hurt productivity and why good managers help it. There’s a metaphor I like that explains the difference between good managers and bad managers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A manager is a multiplier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In software, we have the concept of the 10x developer–the person who can do the work of ten regular developers. While I’m certain that a manager can’t take a functioning team and make it ten times better, they can make things two times better. A 2x manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 2x manager would be rare, but a good managers should make teams slightly better. Making a team 25% better should be considered an accomplishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bad managers have a multiplier of less than one. A 0.5x manager makes a team half as effective as they should be. They hurt teams by creating choke-points, obstacles and distractions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bad managers also hurt teams by causing people to quit. Factoring in the impact of employee leaving, it’s conceivable for a bad manager to have multiplier approaching zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In extreme situations, a bad manager might even have a multiplier below zero. A manager that destroys the value other teams create while also running a team that doesn’t create any value would be an (unlikely) example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the average manager is not a 1x manager. We acknowledge this when we talk about management being a tax on an organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replacing a manager can lead to large shifts of productivity. Going from a bad manager to a good one can feel like a 10x improvement. Conversely, replacing a good manager with a bad one can turn a great team into a poor one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are managing others, you should do anything you can to increase your multiplier.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It’s not always easy to pin down what managers do, but one thing is for sure: bad managers hurt teams. It’s an accepted truth.</summary></entry></feed>